testing excellent okay
I can talk much louder now um okay so
it's it's a pleasure to be here at CFE
and one of the reasons why I am so happy
to come here and kind of talk about my
experience is that CFP has really been a
big part of my own career and the kind
of the work that I've done over the last
kind of 15 years in industry so I came
here at CFP ten years ago that was my
first introduction to this community and
gave a talk about the work that we were
doing at Jane Street at the time and the
somewhat odd decision that we have made
that we had made of going to a kind of
perfectly innocent company and rewriting
their infrastructure in some obscure
functional programming language and I
came to see or fee to kind of talk about
that experience and at the time CFP was
kind of a unique venue in that it was
one of the only places that you could go
to to talk about this kind of work
because there just weren't that many
people in industry kind of taking
functional programming ideas and
applying them to real applications and
there was there weren't natural venues
for people who are doing this kind of
work to come together and meet and see
RFP fill that void and in many ways the
the landscape of functional programming
has changed quite a lot over the years
in that there are now in some sense many
more venues where you can go and talk to
other people who are excited about
functional programming there's like the
code mesh lamda gems strange loop like
long list of all sorts of amusingly
named conferences where there are people
who are really excited about programming
language ideas and excited about
functional programming and but the thing
that I think makes C ofp a kind of
unique place and really kind of more
really more broadly about IC fpm the
kind of all the set of related workshops
is it's a place where the industrial
viewpoint and the practical viewpoint
and the academic viewpoint meet up and
from my perspective that's been a very
kind of productive nexus I've really
kind of made a lot of connections and a
lot of friends in this broader community
and learned an enormous amount from
in sometimes my I feel like think of my
experience that I kind of want to talk
about today is really coming from three
different pots one of those is the
experience I have in the world at Jane
Street and of course that's kind of the
kind of in some sense like the deepest
richest most grounding experience like
the experience of actually trying to do
something at scale with you know with
significant amounts of money at stake
and significant numbers of people and
and that's been a very interesting and
at this point fairly extended process
when I started at Jane Street on 2002
there was something like thirty
employees today there's something like
500 so it's grown quite a bit and the
depth of the reliance on functional
probing programming technologies has
only gotten greater in the years when I
started there I was like doing a little
tiny bit of oh camel on the side for
some research projects certain that the
code I was reading was throwaway code
and you know eighty thousand lines later
it turned out I wasn't going back to be
an academic and you know the code
actually had to be kept around and it
was by the way terrible code and took
many years to unwind all the bad things
I did in the beginning to the kind of
point where we started flipping over our
production infrastructure to using Oh
camel to today where we have you know
something like 80 full-time developers
who program exclusive you know camel
maybe 150 or 200 people for whom a large
part of their job is program you know
camel we kind of shockingly enough have
all of our incoming traders and many
actually people who are hired in other
roles come and spend a month a
month-long Oh camel boot camp where they
have to learn how to use the UNIX shell
and program in Emacs and you know camel
and using our crazy monadic concurrency
libraries and like shockingly it works
sort of an interesting story of its own
so anyway that that kind of experience
of taking functional programming and
Britain making it actually work has been
one thing that's informed me in a big
way the other one is kind of getting
connected to other people who have gone
off into industry to use functional
programming and there's more and more
people who've done that and kind of I've
learned a lot from what I've seen of
what other people have tried in what
succeeded
what hasn't and the other the other pot
from which I feel like I've learned a
lot is the pot of academic functional
programming right I think the the and of
course that's the thing that I CFP kind
of uniquely brings to the table is there
are all these people who are involved in
developing the intellectual framework
under which all of these techniques come
from and in not just the intellectual
framework but actually often the actual
software artifacts come out of academia
and like you know from an industrial
point of view most academic code kind of
sucks
and so it's something of a miracle the
quality of some of the language
implementations that have emerged from
the functional programming community I
think it's a kind of a nice mark for the
the amount of these people care about
the kind of pragmatics of software
engineering and and use a lot of those
ideas in their own work so anyway I
think it's all three of these areas I
think the Jane Street has been a very
exciting place to do functional
programming I think the broader world of
industrial applications has grown a lot
and the academic world has also UIC FP
is the biggest it's ever been that's
also an exciting world and so I think I
kind of want to use those three
perspectives to kind of say a few small
like lessons and observations I've
gotten from that so the first thing I
want to talk about is a kind of
terminological problem that we have in
talking about functional programming
which is when we use the word functional
programming we're often talking about
two different worlds and three core
ideas that animate those worlds in the
two worlds I think of as like the
descendents of Lisp and ml right Lisp is
the older of the two it's the kind of pure
functional programming language although
it wasn't that functional when it first
started invented in the 50s and there's
ml you know a much more sprightly young
language from the mid 70s and and I
think these two languages and their
descendants have been important
and importantly distinct approaches to
programming and when people get up on
stage and say "I use functional
programming" they often mean one or the
other
and it's important to understand that
because the things they say about why
it's valuable are different there's a
core idea that animates both
which is or a few queries this notion
that you should kind of focus on using
pure computation and immutable data
structures and have easy access to
constructs for higher-order computing
right this is the whole like first-class
functions and all of that that's the
thing that animates both of them and is
a kind of important important piece of
both but then each one adds its own
important independent piece and I claim
that independent pieces that are not
each one doesn't quite adopt as well as
they could and should the the advantage
of the other I think the obvious thing
the thing that ml brings is types so the
whole set of kind of ml related
languages in Haskell and Scala and F
sharp and no camel and so on and so
forth the thing that distinguishes them
is the type system right this kind of
formal system of rules that enforces
invariants on your code and informs how
you think about and reason about that
code that's the thing that makes those
languages unique and special and
from my perspective the thing that the
Lisp family really gets right is macros
you really just kind of syntactic
transformations on your code and if you
you look at the two communities they
each I think they each kind of
understand certainly on the academic
side I feel like they each understand
the value of the other's work but don't
quite manage to kind of fully integrate
it like I look forward one day to the
day that oh camel has a macro system
that the racket people won't laugh at
and and similarly that the racket people
have a type system that the ml people
won't look at and see wow that's so much
more complicated than I can understand
right I think that it's it's merging
these ideas together is valuable and I
think it's one of the things that we
kind of see getting better over time I I
hope in my lifetime I will see oh OCaml
have such a macro system but it's it's
it's still at one of these things where
I feel like there are lessons to be
learned by the two sides and it's just
when you hear people talk about you
should understand which of these worlds
are coming from if you want to really
understand the things that they're
saying and in terms of the the kind of I
think people have mostly come to really
appreciate it I said like the values of
the other points of view I think when
you talk to people on the ml side they
don't not have macro systems because
they think they're useless or don't have
great macro they think
it's hard and they don't haven't yet
figured out how to do it in reconcile it
nicely inside a typed language which
raises some extra challenges and I think
increasingly the the kind of dynamically
typed functional language world and in
fact the dynamically typed world has
come to appreciate more the values of
types in fact there's a lot of work
that's come out of this community of how
to kind of gradually add types into
these systems the whole gradual type
systems and like you can hardly like
walk around the programming world
without tripping over a language that
has added a syntax for a type
annotations even Python has one now, you
know. I don't know how far they've gotten
in building actual type system for it
but they started with a syntax so yester
somewhere but anyway those worlds matter
a lot if you want to understand kind of
what happens here at ICFP and I think
either another dynamic that's worth
acknowledging even though it's sometimes
awkward is like actually the ML branch
is ascendant here right if you look at
the papers and look at what people are
writing the vast majority of that work
is from the kind of type family and I
think that's you know some of that I
some of that I think is just kind of
details of how the community works and
some of it is I feel like you know there
probably aren't enough voices from some
of the other parts here as they're kind
of should be but it's sort of useful to
kind of know what the structure of the
community is so before I mentioned this
idea that things have gotten a lot
better there's a lot more activity
there's also you know new conference and
all that but it's actually important to
remember that like it's totally not
popular like functional programming is
still very much a minority activity you
go around and talk to people at schools
and it's way better than it was like
when I was hiring people ten years ago
it was like a coin flip whether a
graduate from a top school would have
ever heard of ml or a related language
and now they've almost all heard of
something in that space and many of them
have been taught it in school but it's
still like an exotic weird thing that
like you know their professors taught
them and there's somewhat suspicious of
its it's still not I think it just feels
like part of the ordinary fabric of the
computing world another evidence of this
you see lots of like sneaky functional
programming projects that can you talk
to people in
they're like yeah I managed to hide this
from my manager it's like a good job
like it's it's sort of there's something
problematic about this view of like you
have to kind of sneak the technology and
it indicates that this something kind of
nascent and incomplete in the kind of
distribution of these ideas and I think
I think that's worth separating is
influenced from popularity which is to
say functional programming has been
enormously influential right if you
look at the design of all sorts of
languages they've been changed a lot by
the ideas and functional programming you
mean even by very old ideas like garbage
collection which landed in LISP before
it landed anywhere else which like you
know took a mere 40 years to go
mainstream it says like quick
transitions but also generics and you
know you see closures and languages like
Java you see type inference showing up
all over the place lots of technology
that originated in functional languages
has spread out into other languages so
that's one form of influence another
form of influences idioms right there
are all sorts of ideas about how to
program that are transportable anywhere
and have been transported so lots of
lots of advice in from people who work
in lots of languages will point out the
value of having immutable data
structures it's a kind of very common
bit of wisdom you'll see frameworks like
react right you know the JavaScript
world like keeps on minting like new
JavaScript frameworks every 45 seconds
but some of the react is one of the more
popular ones it's kind of stuck it seems
to be sticking around and it is deeply
animated by kind of classical functional
programming ideas but I think it's the
the movement of features into other
languages and the movement of ideas into
people's brains I think is not enough
right first of all the when you move
ideas into other languages you only get
a kind of partial reflection of them I
think there's a real difference between
operating in a language which is yay had
closures added to it and operating a
language which was designed from the
ground up for functional programming and
when the idioms move out into other
places the idioms are limited right and
in fact the part that gets to move out
into other languages like that
intersection between the ml and Lisp
world the like the higher-order pure
stuff like that
you can do anywhere with the appropriate
level you can do it and see for God's
sake like you can do but but the whole
disciplines that come from things like
you know high quality macro systems and
that come from high quality type systems
are just not accessible so in some sense
I feel like we shouldn't be satisfied by
the kind of current state of affairs in
the way in which functional languages
are used in practical circumstances a
further limitation of the way in which
functional languages tend to be used in
the real world is where you do go find
like the places where people are using
like well-designed functional languages
for real practical purposes the purposes
are almost always the placement of
lipstick on pigs right which is to say
the prettying up and improving the
experience of working with other kind of
variously broken forms of technology so
and like impressive like you know
awesome industrial scale lipstick on a
pig projects but still lipstick on a pig
right I think one of the if you within
the ocala world which I'm very familiar
with one of the more impressive places
that's done this is Facebook where they
have like a whole bunch of like really
awesome projects to make PHP better oh
right and like the amount of work that's
been poured into PHP is kind of shocking
right to it you know it's like you know
a company has gone in and they use that
technology and like you broke it you
bought it you know it's their thing now
and they have to take care of it and
they do these amazing projects you know
these kind of like the the hack compiler
I remember a demo that I saw where
Julian Veloce who's one of the main guys
behind it
showed me like you do a git rebase and
like changing thousands of files while
they're compiler is incrementally
updating so fast it's done 10
milliseconds after the rebase is
complete right it's working
significantly faster than get can, right.
it's pretty good, right, and it's like a
big parallel or camel program that does
all of this stuff but like it's the
the restriction to a smaller set of
concerns and activities is concerning
right I think in one of my views from
the work that I've done is that that
functional programming is a perfectly
good general purpose tool right you can
be used quite broadly for a wide variety
of projects and it's often limited and
the
which is limited I think are connected
to the academic origins of the field
like you see it limited to compilers and
ESL's and formal methods that's like the
place where you see most of it that's
said it's a thing which is I think
improving and growing over time if you
look at so Jenestreet's one example of
a sort of completely general purpose
kind of place that's using functional
programming whatsapp's use of air Lange
is another kind of famous example of
this Twitter and Scala and then there's
like the people who are coming up with
new languages like Apple with Swift and
Mozilla with Rust are both kind of early
and very sweet but still interesting
places that have kind of repackaged
these ideas in somewhat different ways
and kind of trying to push them towards
doing practical and fairly
general-purpose stuff and in fact a key
Facebook itself is also has some
internal projects to try and push the
use of OCaml for ordinary programming
rather than for kind of special purpose
language kind of work so I think this is
an ongoing in ongoing process and this
progress that's been made but it's still
quite incomplete so one of the questions
is why like what yeah I'm personally
deeply convinced that functional
programming is great probably lots of
you are too and why doesn't everyone
else agree and I think there's a kind of
fundamental fact that there's no
evidence you basically can't convince
anybody like in for good reasons like
you really can't convince anyone because
there's there is no good way of
obtaining experimental evidence about
this. like imagine designing the
experiment that would prove that you
know programming language technology A
is better than programming technology B
it's like you guys in this side are
going to be randomizing to grew the
group that's doing their project in
COBOL for two years and you you know
know like no one's going to do that like
the the only thing that matters in
programming are the things that
happen with experience and scale and you
can't get experience and scale in the
lab, right. the only experimental
instruments that you have, if you're
doing stuff in university, is like
sophomores and there's no pile of
sophomores high enough to prove anything
about what it's like to be an actual
programmer because they're doing small
things and they're, you know,
there's a small time scale involve
so the experiment evidence is incredibly
hard to come by and in some sense I
don't think we should be surprised
because I think that, in some sense,
the wrong expectations come from the
the name of our overall field it's
computer science it's like you know any
field that has to call itself a science
you should be a little dubious of and, I
think, Computer Science is in many ways a
kind of mathematical engineering
discipline and if you look at
programming language design in
particular, I think, it's more of a kind
of mathematical design oriented thing.
it's closer to Architecture than it is
to experimental physics, I think that, and
so you don't get, you don't get to
the expectation that you're going to
have scientific ways of evaluating these
things because the things that are being
done are too fundamentally human in
nature, too fundamentally social and I
think this is actually a fundamental
problem for programming language learn. I
think it helps explain that disturbing
40-year gap between when garbage
collection was invented and when it
started being used in the mainstream way
is because it's very hard to convince
people and people are very much in their
own heads, right. It's hard for them to
appreciate the things that they don't
understand, right. I think this is a key a
general problem of it's very hard to
value technologies especially
programming language ideas that you
don't already deeply understand and I
think this is a serious problem for
people who want to kind of push and
evangelize functional programming
because it's it's so hard to convince
somebody that it's better like you can
explain to them how it works you can
show them a small example and you can
tell them you know your success story
and by the success stories like, I mean
in some ways, this conference
specializes in success stories and
sometimes failure stories experience but
successors are interesting to look at.
but they're not convincing, right, because
for every one functional programming
success story there's ten imperative
programming success stories, right, and as
we know popularity isn't... it's not like
you should thereby be convinced at
imperative programming, right, we know
that popularity is a bad guide to what
to do like see previous comment about
garbage collection, right, so popularity
can't be the guide and so it's... it's... it's
hard to convince people who haven't
fully
used and really experienced the
ideas in question. And it's when this is
not just like a thing to say about those
dumb imperative programming people, it's
true about all of us - like I've
experienced this myself in ways that
have been somewhat humbling so one of my
favorite experiences in this regard was
at some point a new feature was added to
a camel generalised algebraic data types
and I was not excited. I thought: "Oh, this
is the kind of garbage you get when you
let compiler writers design your
programming language" like some... like
fancy-schmancy type system nonsense that
lets them more precisely express... blah
blah blah. I'm already sleeping... like... I'm
a systems programmer, I don't care about
like all sorts of fancy type system
things, like. I want you know, I want the
better help messages and a faster
compiler and better inlining and like
can we please stop working on the type
system. And it turns out I was kind of
wrong, like... GADT's, do you know what
they're really good for? optimization!
like writing... you want to write like a
thing that can process you know a couple
million messages a second and get a
message in and out in five MKBps. you
should learn how to use GADT's which was
surprising. Like I did not expect that it
turns out GADT's are a really good tool
for controlling memory representation
and not a thing I'd known about and not
a thing I'd understood. Another
thing that was added with GADT's was
that was good support for using
existentially quantified type variables
in OCaml which like sounds about as like
nerdy pointy-headed like what is
essentially like orient math class again
but it turns out existentially
quantified type variables are really
useful and I had I knew what they were
and I had come to understand that
because ml didn't have them in a clean
and easy to access way oh camel didn't
have them and I'd learned they're so
standard ways of kind of working around
it and like you know you get a record
full of closures that hide the
underlying thing and everything works
out, and it turns out that totally sucked
like it didn't perform very well it was
hard to know the code was harder to
write. existencial were much cleaner and
much more natural and I kind of had like
dismissed them out of hand without
really fully understanding them. and so I
think this kind of highlighted to me the
idea that you really want to
think broadly about the other kind of
ideas that are out there and try and
understand and inhabit the understanding
of other programming language
communities and maybe you know that
thing and some other language that you
think isn't very valuable maybe you
should try it, and try and live in those
shoes for a little while and see if
there's something that you can pick up
and steal and bring back to your own
work. Another thing people commonly like
to talk about and in particular, I think,
people who are in this place of like
trying to get functional programming
used in some practical context and what
they're in is they say you know we
should use the right tool for the job
and the right tool for this job is say a
functional programming language. And I
have some sympathy for this idea after
all
should we use the wrong tool for the job?
right of course we use the right tool
for the job! but I think that the the
whole suggestion is in some sense
animated by a kind of mistaken idea and
I think there's two different mistaken
ideas that animate it. one is: the the
idea that that we need lots of different
tools because different jobs require
different tools, because you know there's
just like you know we need a big
complicated tool bet that you wear
around your you know where around your
waist it like gives all the different
tools you can do for solving the
different jobs and I think it turns out
that's mostly a mistake in the sense.
that yeah there are some you need some
variety of tools all you should use one
programming language for every single
thing that you do but there are
programming language techniques that are
more broad spectrum than others that can
solve more kinds of problems and you're
better off picking those when you can
because because it affects the
organization that you're in, it makes
that organization better. why? well
because you want to maximize various
forms of sharing and flexibility and
just kind of the power of the individual
developer and the organization that
you're in, and having a small number of
tools that people can really develop
expertise in and develop tools for right
you know your programming language is a
tool but you need tools for that tool
and so that and and develop shared
standards so that people can walk into
some other code base and understand how
it works right so that people are kind
of transportable between different areas.
that's enormously freeing like one
something you find sometimes here is
like oh we went off and built XYZ and
language W that nobody uses and it's
great although I have this chain tying
me to that project and I can never leave
because nobody else knows the language.
right like that's awkward and you don't
want to be stuck in that situation and
it's not a thing you want for your
organization and so I think that you
know people are with people who are in
organizations that have very strong
requirements and standards on which
languages they use. Google sort of famous
for having for right you can program in
C++ and you can program in Python you
can program in Java and you can program
in Go, and while I somewhat in like
occasionally again you can like hide
from your managers and do something else
but like mostly that's it and while I
don't especially approve of the concrete
list of choices I think the fact that
they keep it down to a small list is
totally rational right I think if you
want to have a good software engineering
experience. the ability to kind of focus
down on a small set of languages, I think,
really helps you do a better job of that
and I think that this is the kind of
thing that that really depends on scale.
and many things about programming depend
on scale. you know when you first if you
start out like you're doing a small
thing in a small company and the
individual speed with which you can do
stuff is in some sense the dominant
factor, it's like what can be comfortable
what makes me able to do my job best. and
you can sort of go by that and be pretty
happy for a while, but as you get if
you're going to do anything really big
significant you need other people right
programming is social it's collaborative
and as you try and increase the scale at
which you're working on things, well, you
need to the you need to deal with the
fact that the constant shift around, the
expense is change, right, you get more
costs that come from interactions right
as you have a big system with lots of
pieces and lots of people involved when
you change individual pieces, right, that
can break other things and something
that pushes you in the direction of
different choices about tools and
different choices about how you organize
things. and so I think it's an important
thing to think about when you're picking
technology is not just what it means for
you but what it means for the overall
organization
and for us that's actually affected
a lot the way that we think about how we
kind of invest in not just the language
that we use but the tools surrounding it.
like over time we've spent a lot more
time and energy thinking about language
tools and testing, right, and you know the
OCaml type system is a wonderful thing
and it catches lots of bugs for you and
you can skate away with like not quite
enough testing for a surprisingly long
time. and we kind of did that for a while
and then over time as things got more
complicated and the stakes got higher
we're like that that was dumb and we
started really investing in other kinds
of tools and that turns out to be kind
of incredibly important as you get
bigger and you need to change how you
behave. and but the other thing that
required more tools like early on we had
we had like lots of functional
programming people who we had hired to
do the work in the functional
programming language. which was great and
in fact that's one of the advantages for
us had been of using these kind of
languages is you know the set of
functional programmers is roughly empty
but the people in that empty set are
pretty good and so there was a real
advantage of hiring of pulling in high
quality people by virtue of the language
that we were using. but you know as we
got bigger we started hiring people in
more diverse ways, hiring more kids out
of school who weren't already like baked
in functional programmers, and also
teaching people to program who weren't
really by nature programmers at all,
right it turns out learning have if
you're a technical person who's capable
learning how to program. learning how to
program badly... is incredibly valuable!
like we had made a lot of money from
like lots of terrible code that people
have written you know to solve their own
narrow problem maybe not in a kind of
scalable and sustainable way but in a
way that locally worked for them and the
small group of people they were working
in. and you also have to change how you
invest when you're trying to grow beyond
like that core group of like-minded
people who've gone who are there for the
particular technology to a broader set
of people who are there for all sorts of
other reasons. And if that this feeds
into another kind of larger kind of "you
broke it you bought it" phenomenon. right.
so I mentioned this about Facebook where
that happened with them with PHP so
happened with us with OCamel and
because I'm also happier about that
particular ownership story... but but the
you it in some sense using a minority
language.... like that's actually the hard
part you think oh using functional
programming in the world that's hard no
it's not the functional programming
parts easy that makes your life better
the part that's hard is being a minority
language being, having the poorer set of
tools and the poor set of libraries and
the poor sort of shared understanding
that comes from being small, and when you
enter into a world like this and you
succeed, you sort of have bought a
requirement to do something about it,
right. and that's something that's
happened to us is that we kind of
recognize fairly early that you know as
our kind of use of account will ramped
up and as the business ramped up we
needed to really invest in the broader
community, and we've tried to adopt a
kind of point of view of like
enlightened self-interest about this.
which is to say we've tried to take the
broad view that the overall community
around the language is important and we
need to support it and it's important to
our success but we don't need to support
it narrowly so, for example, we've spent a
lot of time funding the building of
infrastructure that we're never going to
use, right, so this is great tool in
OCaml which we didn't write but which we
funded the work by OcamlPro which is a
commercial services company right called
OPAM which is a package manager before Oh
Pam it was an embarrassing thing to have
to explain to someone how to install a
camel I remember doing a tutorial at sea
a few years ago where I felt like I
brought out my like my burlap sack full
of tar balls and like emptied them out
on the table and tada you can probably
figure this out and you know we spent
like the first two hours or something
just installing stuff. it's horrible. now
okay Oh Pam install blah blah and things
work and that's transformative but we
don't use it it has no role in our
internal infrastructure but the
community has a role in our world, like I
think we've benefitted enormous amount
from the work that the kind of core
contributors to your calomel itself have
done and people building libraries and
people building tools all sorts of great
stuff has come our way because the
community is like alive and active and
successful. and you know we tried to
support it by evangelizing and giving
talks and releasing our own soft
supporting the stuff that other people
do, and I think it's worked out
extraordinarily well for us I think it's
it's helped the the community that we
depend so much on become more vibrant.
it's helped us hire people and I think
it's something I kind of recommend to
organizations that are in this position.
like if you really depend on a
technology you shouldn't make an overly
narrow calculation of like ah well you
know if I spend this much money what do
I don't get any product back out of it
so it's not worth it, right? it turns out
I think that these communities have a
lot of value and you know they'll take
your concerns more seriously if you kind
of openly contribute back to them and I
think it's for for companies that are
involved in minority languages I think
it's a really valuable kind of mindset
to take. another observation, so I was
talking before about the relationship
between kind of academia and industrial
work. and I think that's a really
productive perspective and I think lots
of you will sometimes hear people in
industry being like oh uh academia
they're all off heads in the sky doing
stuff that doesn't matter for practical
work and I really think this isn't true.
I think that in fact I feel this
actually about loss of academic
disciplines my own home field is
distributed systems and I feel like I
learned an enormous amount for the work
I did there that was a practical import.
like even though I didn't go off like
writing Paxos algorithms for doing
distributed consensus, nonetheless the
kind of insights and and intellectual
organization that came from that world I
found enormously informative, and I feel
very much the same way about the
programming language community. in fact a
thing I find kind of surprising and like
mildly frustrating is how sensible the
the academic community. I feel like you
know I've I've been off like in industry
doing practical stuff for over a decade,
like you know I've had a lot of hard-won
lessons about what's the right way of
approaching thing and how do you solve
problems, and the degree to which like
you know I go off and talk to the sort
of you know senior  people in the
programming language community about how
things should be done in the amount of
like shared ideas and and and concept. is
like surprisingly high it's like how do
they get there like they're just writing
compilers and like papers and stuff like
how do they know anything about software
engineering? but I think there's a
there's a part of what's going on is
this
surprising there's a the
languages are kind of surprisingly kind
of well fit to the problem space, which
in a way which I think is sort of
accidental. Like, I think, is... I
think, I think, that
Phil Wadler has talked about before but
I think the good programming
languages were more invented, were more
discovered than invented and I think the
people who discovered them kind of got
lucky in some sense like they were like
you know working in a good space things
that had nice mathematical structure and
the kind of Help together. but the fact
that ml and its descendants are such
good pragmatic programming languages in
some senses I think dumb luck like. there
were lots of other programming languages
that people invented that turned out not
to be as as good and I don't I don't
think like people sort of thought in
advance and had you know deep reasons to
know that these were the right things. I
think there's a certain amount of a
certain amount of luck that fell in
there. but in any case I think it turns
out that the academic world that thinks
about these languages has a lot of
practical useful things to say and some
of it is on the design of the language
themselves, and some of it is on the ways
in which you should use them, in the kind
of idioms that are useful, like one thing
that I've had kind of personally a very
productive back-and-forth on with lots
of people and the academic world is on a
kind of incremental and reactive
programming. where there's a whole bunch
of work that people have done about how
to think about structuring incremental
programs and that turns out to be a
really important pragmatic problem for a
lot of different things, right. if you're
building you know trading systems or
you're building user interfaces or lots
of other kinds of calculations you might
want to do, this notion of having
programs that can efficiently react to
new information is a kind of fundamental
problem, and it turns out the academic
perspective on this was very valuable.
and like there's a system that we built
internally called incremental, where we
wrote the first version without really
reading the paper carefully and we made
a lot of mistakes and you know going
back and looking at the papers helped
and there were lots of things that we
were able to fix by kind of
understanding the kind of academic
perspective and the ideas that people
had kind of carefully thought through.
it's worth saying it's also true in the
other direction I think there's a lot
that academia can learn from
practitioners, I guess somehow in that in
that in some of that same work I think
there's lots of there were lots of
semantics
that we got wrong in our first versions.
and lost performance ideas that the
author's got wrong, and, you know I think
some of this difference in information
comes from difference in focus. there are
just certain kinds of problems that
academics don't kind of fully have
access to. some of them are have to do
with exactly what problem space you're
looking at, like there are certain kinds
of performance problems that academics
happen not to look at, and practice some
practitioners do care about, and that's
one kind of information difference that
goes the other way. Another thing that I
think academics have very poor access to
in some sense is the problems that come
at scale. so when you think about how do
I deal with versioning and code review
and testing and various other like
software engineering stuff that matters
when you get when you when you're trying
to build multi-million line code bases.
there's a queue very little experience
in academia there's a whole bunch of
interesting problems there, that you know
see previous comment about like academic
code is usually not that good there's
really not that much code review
involved a lot of those things. like
those infrastructure just not ones
that they've had an opportunity to kind
of really dig into and understand, and so
I think there's a really kind of
productive space for both of these
worlds to talk to each other and share
information, and, I think, whichever side
you're on I think it's worth seeking out
people from the other side the other
thing that academics can learn from
practitioners is kind of something about
like what what things matter. right, I
think academic start out with pretty
good intuitions about kind of what are
reasonable ways of designing programming
languages but I think in the field when
you're using it with a large number of
people on that scale, like you learn all
sorts of things about what things can be
talked to people on what things can't
and, what features are too complicated
for people to use in practice, and what
kind of techniques actually meld very
well and are easy to show people. and I
think, programming languages really is as
I said it's kind of a human oriented
design problem in addition to being a
mathematical problem. and I think it's
important for the academic side to pay
attention to the human side. and the
practitioners have most of the humans
that are kind of doing doing programming
at big scale, I think it's worth more
communication there.7
so another kind of aspect of the kind of
practical use of programming language in
the real world is teaching them and I've
thought about teaching in a lot of ways
in my life like sometimes literally with
my own kids. I have I have three kids all
of whom I have taught on a surprisingly
wide variety of different programming
languages at this point. and that itself
is a super exciting kind of adventure to
go through and, by the way, if you want
good idea for a project to do with your
kids text adventures, I recommend text
adventure they're super fun. but there's
also the issue of teaching of functional
programming in schools which I think is
one of the ways in which these ideas are
distributed and I think an important
thing like if you care about functional
languages getting more traction and
being used more and being a more kind of
real part of the computational world.
then you should care about the
educational side of this, and I feel like
the story that has around this has is
both kind of good and improving but also
sort of tenuous, which is to say you like
I go I actually go around and have had
the privilege of giving talks at a whole
bunch of different universities that
teach some variant of ML as part of
their kind of major curriculum as a
thing that everybody goes through. and
there's a kind of shocking number of
them, right, brown and CMU and Cornell and
Princeton and Harvard and some other a
bunch of like major US universities and
a lot of universities in Europe as well
and probably other places I'm not
thinking, of teach functional programming
as a kind of core important part of the
curriculum. but there's something sort of
tenuous about this state of affairs
which is to say the functional
programming itself is not necessarily
widely kind of recognized and understood
as a as a kind of important and valuable
discipline, and even in departments that
have very strong kind of functional
programming contingents, there's often
some other part of the department that
looks suspiciously at the functional
programming people and the main reason, I
think, that so many of these schools
teach functional programming is because
the people who care most about
programming are the people who study
programming
they're often the ones who are willing
to take the time to teach the courses,
and so anyway like this is sort of all
academic inside baseball why does it
matter, I think the reason it matters is
if you care about the kind of language
community being successful, I think you
should care about how that how those
languages are kind of useful and usable
in academia, and I think that requires
some real focus on tooling that can be
used by people who are teaching. I think
teaching languages is hard , you know,
there's and there's lots of
infrastructure to help people out like
in in mainstream languages. like you go
and use Java and you have all these kind
of really awesome ideas that help you
explore things and help you find things
and like yeah there's a lot of.
boilerplate too right but like there's a
button that generates a bunch of it and
people are often made sort of happy by
that. and then even separate from the
concrete tools there are other
advantages that that we can't have like
Stack Overflow, like you want to know a
thing about some major language, either
go to stack overflow and search it and
you will find like bajillions of answers.
and you want to know something about a
relatively obscure kind of minority
language and that's a lot thinner on the
ground. and ... you can't all at once
manufacture that kind of shared
knowledge base in kind of off in the
web but you can make your tools better
and I think making tools better in a way
that optimizes towards learning I think
is really helpful. and this is the thing
that we've had a lot of kind of internal
kind of experience and success with it
as well and that we mentioned we have
this kind of OCAml boot camp where we teach a
bunch of non-programmers.
I mean some programmers and some non
programmers but not functional
programmers to program in our world and
it's gotten massively easier over the
years. and one of the reasons it's gotten
easier is because we've invested a lot
in the tools and again that's kind of an
overall thing that I feel like I've
learned over the years is that tools are
incredibly important, like many good
things about languages can be swamped by
bad tools. if you want a good evidence
for how important tools are compared to
languages look at Go, which is frankly
uninspiring programming language, who's
like you know ideas were like fresh in
1968 but
it's just like doesn't have that much to
offer, but the tooling is awesome! and I
know lots of people including people who
are happy functional programmers feel
like yeah this go thing it's not bad. I
mean yeah I wish I had sent a higher
order anything in good you know
parametric polymorphism and all this
stuff and but you know what the tools
don't suck and and that that's
incredibly valuable. and I think it's
it's easy from a kind of point of view
that like values the language, it's easy
to underestimate the point of view of
tools. so I guess kind of one kind of
final point I want to make is that when
you're off wanting to do practical
things and take functional languages and
make good real-world use of them. it's
often it's often tempting to focus on
evangelism, I'm trying to convince people
I'm trying to get other people to do
things and, I think that is a hard
proposition in kind of a losing game in
some sense. people are hard to convince
and the world moves very slowly,  right. I
think getting ideas out there I think
you know you can do it and I think this
community has chipped away at it over
the years and pushed forward a lot of
these ideas and gotten a lot more uptake
on it, but it can take sometimes like, you
know, glacial timeframes, right, you know
again like parametric polymorphism mid
70s invented hit mainstream languages
2000 2000 something right whenever like
generics hit Java again like 35 years or
something, gap between invention and use.
so, well, I think it's it's great to think
long term about how you can help spread
the ideas, I think short terms, you know,
just succeed right these languages are
incredibly valuable tools you can use
them for making your own life in your
own organization better. and by doing so
you can you know build another one of
these success stories. it won't exactly
be convincing, right, as I said success
stories don't really prove anything but
they add up over time. and in the
meantime you can have like a great
profitable business that does wonderful
things and you get to work with tools
that don't make you want to claw your
eyes out. and I think that's that's a
it's a it's a kind of short-term
strategy that
you can all kind of take and just kind
of do the thing with our own hands
that makes us the most effective. Snd
with that I'm happy to take questions.
oh, hi! it's more of a comment than a
question. you mentioned that's you found
it open but you don't use you don't use
OPAM. and you also released a lot of
packages on github but have you tried
building those packages using the tools
that a OCaml programmers have and not
your internal tools. it's it can be quite
tough and a lot of them, I had a couple
of cases where, it's like, I saw a cool
package on github I pull it out I pull
it down, and it just doesn't compile and
then I have to figure out like okay what
do I have to tweak here what do I have
to tweak there and here's the couple of
lines of code I need to delete to make
it work.
using a ocamlbuild or interest in my
local environment. so the question is
there's a comments like so you're at
least a lot of packages but do you try
building them using the tools that other
people have recently we do actually we
have there's a lot of work in the OCaml
world for making kind of continuous
integration testing for OPAM packages
and actually these days when I do like
an open upgrade and install our stuff it
usually works pretty smoothly at least
on the Mac which is where I do stuff at
home. and so yeah we've been doing a lot
of work to make that integration
smoother. and in fact I think the primary
thing we're doing that's going to really
make that really work is we've taken a
bunch of our internal tools like Jenga
which is a build system that we had -
that we wrote internally. a fact about
which I'm deeply embarrassed like the
idea that a company today should write
its own build system is ridiculous but
there are no good build systems. it's
sort of crazy but anyway so we wrote we
wrote our own build system and we're
we've we've now done a bunch of work to
make it usable outside and we're gonna
start releasing our packages externally
using the same
we use internally. but the reason we
don't use open is I think a subtle one
that I think people who work in kind of
more intensely like the kind of working
on stuff that's more purely open-source
often don't fully understand which is
that the lots of companies ourselves
included have found it's incredibly
useful to have single very large
repositories for managing their codebase
that's kind of what's called a mono repo
approach, which turns out to be massively
a massively simplifying technique and
like Google and Facebook and lots of
other places do this and we do it too
and that's incompatible with things like
OPAM's workflow and like the the
downside is you have to do some work to
cross that impedance barrier of figuring
how to kind of push things to the open
source world. the upside is you get to
build your source code without ever
having to say the word constraint solver
right which totally sucks right. it's
just a much simpler version you can say
like what's the version of the world
this single hash tells me everything
that's an incredibly powerful kind of
software engineering move. hi@ Tyler dramaski
from fugue. I had a question you
mentioned going from using okay ml is
kind of like an experimental language in
Jane Street to now it's you know the
language is James Street it's used
everywhere I was kind of wondering what
it was like crossing that tipping point
where you guys knew that you were
invested and especially when it comes to
the tooling being able to make the
business justification of... aaa... writing the
tooling internally versus like moving to
a language where there is that tooling
already exists. yeah so yeah change is a
pretty a pretty good place and a pretty
rational place and one of the things I
have loved about my professional life
there is that by and large the major
work I had to do to convince other
people that we needed to do something
was to first convince myself and once I
had an argument that made sense to me it
was pretty easy to get other people to
come on board. we didn't like the the
move to OCaml was taken after like some
serious thought and some discussion and
you know looking at statistics about how
vital the community was, and thinking
about like how practical we move this
was and thinking
other companies had done. the move to do
more tooling work has been incremental
and has been justified by the effects
piece-by-piece like it's somewhat you're
like. oh we're in spent some time getting
tooling anyone and all the people who
are working are like oh this is so much
better and I'm so much more productive
you're like. okay we should do more of
this and by trying to kind of rationally
engage with the question of what's the
best thing for the company we're able to
kind of realize that we just needed to
do more of us. so Yaron you talked about
gathering evidence for the value of the
functional programming.
well Jane Street is in a very good
position to do that but to do so
convincingly you probably need to
collaborate not with people from the PL
community but with people from the
empirical software engineering community.
I wonder if you have any such studies
going on or whether there's an
opportunity there. So we don't have the
studies going on and I am and I'd love
to talk about this later but I'm
actually deeply dubious about this in
principle. like I think when I look at
the James Street experience around
software engineering I think what better
evidence is there a functional
programming being great. where we had a
company which didn't use functional
programming and then we brought it in
and like you know we had this much
objectively much better software
infrastructure after all that work and
an incredibly successful company that we
really depended on that software in a
fundamental way. clearly functional
programming is great but actually
there's no evidence at all from that.
right. because the people doing the
rewrite were different people and it was
a rewrite which is always better even
with the Saint well not oh it's better
but you have a lot of new opportunities
on a rewrite sometimes it's worse and
like we put new people and new energy in
a different time, like, there's nothing
like a controlled experiment here. and
now though you come into ghu today and
like oh my god selection bias like we
have hired differently from other
organizations we have all sorts of
differences in our behavior. and I just
don't know as a scientific matter how
you to construct any kind of useful
empirical data from the work that we do.
so I've talked some with people kind of
on the side and I've never come away
with the something that seemed to me
like a kind of technique that seemed
kind of well-founded and that... thought
would be like that if the results came
out and I saw them I would believe them
and India I think exactly probably
results come out and people say oh that
one violates my prior belief so I'm
gonna find ways I don't believe in the
study. and I guess don't believe in any of
the studies including the ones that
confirm my beliefs because I think
social science is hard and Social
Sciences about things that are too
expensive to do like make people switch
to make large teams of people switch
programming languages seem nearly
impossible. that's you
A Clipper Good from Google I have a
comment on the last I think the last
slide sorry I didn't drink my coffee
today yet sorry okay so so use advantage
there is a it works but only if the
organization you're in is not too big. if
the organization is big enough there is
so much existing, so much existing
infrastructure without which you cannot
use the tool of your choice because
there is no integrations. so, yes, module
this slide that's right, yeah -- I think, I
think you're absolutely right --
there is often a chicken neck problem if
you're big enough there is no
infrastructure you can use the
infrastructure to do good projects there
is no good projects there is no reason
for infrastructure that exists
specifically about I'm talking about a
Haskell to Google and yeah this is a
really tough right one. -- Yeah I think
that's right I mean I think if you if
you if you really want to be able to
kind of make your own choices about
technology I think there's two things
you can do right you can you know start
your own place and do your own small
thing and build things the way you want
to and then you can start small and
build from there
or you can do the hard you know laudable
work of convincing an organization to do
something new. One of the reasons I'm
actually like kind of upset about Go as
a language is not because it's a bad
language is an OK language, but it's very
rare that a company takes the
opportunity to like build a big new
language and like it's a depressingly
kind of small amount of progress to have
done in that move, right, and I think that
you know there are people in various
larger companies who are
trying to do the work to build
institutional infrastructure for using
functional programming and, I think,
that's great but I think just saying, oh
I'm gonna do it on my own and find a way
to hide it from my manager, it's like for
I'd only good career move I don't know
like I think you know if you want to if
you want to do well it's great to
optimize for the organization you're in
rather than just optimize for the thing
that's like technically the most fun for
you. So, I think, as you say I don't think
you can take Jane Street to be some
proof that using a functional language
guarantees success but you can't take it
as a proof that it doesn't guarantee
failure -- I agree, I agree, and I think many
people imagine that failure is the only
option when using function languages is
certainly for the kind of work that we
do, I think, lots of people think well
clearly that's not going to work and it
turns out no, actually big successful
business totally works. (Q) Charles Mike (?)
from X. in terms of sort of spreading our
wings conceptually what languages do you
think in this community
community aren't looking at that we
should? for that matter to include things
like NGO -- (Y) so I think I think I think
there I often feel like there's
insufficient communication I think I
mentioned earlier between like the typed
and untyped. so I think there's a lot to
the ml community and I mean ML like you
know in this is ml and Lisp right I'm
not dying me to exclude like Haskell and
Scala or whatever but I think the the
the statically type world could learn a
lot from the things that are understood
about macro systems, I think macro
systems are really incredibly valuable
and learning how that works is great I
think a thing which I feel like I should
learn more about is some of the kind of
more proof oriented systems that kind of
Agda and Coq of the world which I've
learned little bits about but I
mentioned learning more yeah that's
that's what comes to mind I don't I
don't have like a super long list of
things it's just I kind of in general
try and like when I learn about new
things kind of poke around and try and
see how they work and like wordsworth
also look at like systems that you don't
think are going to be great.
like, I think that looking at and
understanding what it is about the world
of Go that's so compelling because it
really is in many ways very compelling
looking at the JavaScript world and how
they manage software and how they manage
packaging which I think is a mix of
great and terrible but I think there's
some things to be learned from there. so
I think some stuff within the functional
programming world and some stuff from
outside of it and actually and another
thing you should learn from like C++ and
C about performance and about what are
the things what are the things that C
programmers do to make things go fast
and understand how you can make your
language capable of doing those things
that's another I think important area
where it's easy to get like, oh I'm often
my like you know high-higher type
dependent lead lambda calculus in the
sky kind of thing and like not think
about machines. and you should also think
about machines (Q) yarn Hendrika a
Commonwealth Bank one of the things that
I grapple with is how hard to push FP in
general in the context of this
conversation at non-specialists. the
example I'm thinking of is the machine
learning community where they really
love R and Python and the problem that
we've been using the tooling as the
metaphor for the things we don't have in
this conversation but in this case, like
the the our world is one I look at where
like what is so exciting in our land
that keeps these reasonably intelligent
people doing sanely stupid things
because you look at the the idiot that
the code they construct it's it's awful.
and yet they get the outcomes they need
and so my question is is where do you
think because I know like it by
reputation anyway Jane Street does a lot
of work to help new hires who aren't
core programmers come on board at least
with to be able to share the lingua
franca working in your case OCAML
I've tried that before in Haskell it
works really well. but I'm sort of up
against the line where like if I if I go
one step further we've got a turns out a
big scholarship, okay, but if we go one
further and try and get the data
scientists to be doing things in a way
we can put in production it kind of
implies they work in Scala or Haskell.
and they're not there at the moment and
I'm sort of nervous about that should we
be tolerating them continue to work in
our and tooling around that or should we
be trying to drag them off of our and
numpy and so on and reimplemented the
machine learning infrastructure in our
languages. and I'm just curious how you
feel about that class of problem. (Y) yeah I
mean I think that's actually very hard
to give you a sense of why I think it's
hard like we haven't succeeded in doing
it like we still use R for things
because there's lots of nice integration
of all sorts of little packages. and like
ecosystems are valuable and it's hard to
replicate those ecosystems. So, I'm like
I'm more optimum I think I'm I'm more
optimistic about teaching people how to
use functional programming. but taking
like powerful ecosystems that have lots
of built-in functionality and replacing
them, like.... I think that's really hard and
I think you need to have a really like
in some of that I feel like you take it
from what are you like inhabiting their
perspective think about their daily
workflow. and think would it really be
easier in this programming language and
like often the answer is no often it's
just easier for them to like throw act
together they're our thing and like you
know don't recommend to people things
that don't make them more effective. (Q) hi
Eric Tora Bora um though what are the
things that are coming up - a camel
maybe in the next three four five years
that are coming from the academia into
the language that you are really excited
about that's going to change your life
as a practitioner... (Y) there ah
interesting so a thing that has a thing
that has been like lots of collaboration
between us and between the academic
world is flambda which is a better
inlining pasture of OCAML kind of
improving your camels optimization so
that's I think an exciting thing there's
been a lot of work that's happened from
outside of our walls on improving kind
of IDE like functionality in OCamel
and that kind of getting like integrated
and upstream with a compiler and stuff
is the thing that kind of makes the kind
of day-to-day working really lovely.
there's a couple another another big
thing that's coming which I'm pretty
excited about is modular implicit's --
which is essentially a form of type
class like functionality for ML that
kind of fits better inside of an ML
language. and I think that will be quite
useful.
another another interesting one is
there's some work on effects tracking
in OCaml which I am both skeptical
and excited about like I think it could
be good and it could be problematic I
see lots of the new things are
interesting in that they open up
enormous enormous issues of like how you
design libraries which are complicated
questions and then I think it'll take
time to unwind. So like the language
feature comes first and you learn how to
use it later sometimes years later.
actually I think one of the great one of
the fascinating if you want to
understand how people learning how to
use languages develops go look at like
the implementation of a functional
programming compiler from 20 years ago
and... they're often kind of a mess like
they didn't know how to use a lot of the
features that the languages themselves
had in like over time people have come
to understand this goes back the idea of
like these languages and sometimes feel
like they were invented by mistake, like
all the great things about them were not
fully apparent at the time of their
writing and I think some of the things
that are coming we won't know like GADT's
and first-class modules were things
that landed recently which I'm very
happy about the next thing that comes
that I may be happy about maybe not
something I know is going to be good all
(Organizer) right, let's think run!